The class, so I say I decided to.
The restaurant.
So.
I think I can share the screen.
There we are.
So first of all, few no on Monday.
We will do another round of exercise.
For the coming project,
I expect to propose the overview with the
project that should be done in no more
than.
Let's say 10 days, not full time. OK,
so that so that you can allocate your
time.
My my point is not to to renew in in this.
It is more to challenge you and spend
some time and learning something and
force you to do procedures that are
uncommon. OK, so don't don't worry,
most of the exam will be the oral exam.
For which please starting and try to be
as prepared as you can be.
Uh.
I'm still generating the notes and they
are coming.
You still have video transcriptions and
etcetera. So and you can find the.
Yeah.
OK.
You can find it on the web documentation,
whatever,
but please there are the notes from
Andrea also the previous year because at
the end of the day.
We COVID the pretty much.
Similar set of topics.
The main point that I really care for you
is please try to understand two things,
the abstract concept. I don't care.
Nothing about.
I don't know active workflows in a chart
or a sync in C# or promises in JavaScript.
I mean today there are these two years
and there will be something else. OK,
so there's no but you.
Must focus on the idea that that
particular scene that hides in the behind
and so try to understand if you want to
start studying and I mean and try to see
if you get it.
Ask yourself questions. I mean,
I'd like to have monads,
but I'm working in Rasta.
How can I have a monadic style
computation expressly in Rasta?
That's the right question.
OK,
this raster for me with this or should I
implement the runtime because there is no
sufferings?
OK, so these are basically and so the.
The the the project will try to push you
on these with the help of the eye,
which is really valuable because before
the only option was to go to the library,
take the book or go to the.
Later, years later, take a book,
read your book, and if you're lucky,
learn something more. If you're unlucky,
no. OK,
so AI can be a super big asset to
implement to learn.
Things,
but you have to do try yourself and you
have to understand the right questions.
Can you explain me the scoping policy of
the Python PROGRAMMING language and so on
so.
In this way you can find yourself the
question. So my personal goal is this.
I can tell you.
I'm talking to more and more in
industries and everyone is after the code
through AI so.
It's important that you spend time there.
OK,
so there will be basically I I spent some
time thinking into the details.
There will be basically three kind of
projects.
So one,
I mean all the same generate the outputs,
I mean the output,
the prompts and the check always. OK,
basically I found that it is useful to
classify tasks in three.
Categories. One is software generation,
so some of the project will be generating
software Excel.
Be doable, but not too easy.
And then you submit the code with the
problems and some consideration about how
do you think it was?
Another one is explore feature X or
language Y or system Y.
That's another one.
The third one is explore system X and
tell me something about it as we did with
the CLR. OK,
and in that case you will do a little bit
of copy testing.
Back and forth to ask questions about
some feature of the of the thing. No, no,
it will be only one assignment,
which of course I will share in the.
And uh,
it's a it's a single exam that's OK.
And since me and Andrea,
we are on different side of the spectrum
in so many ways,
I think it will be interesting,
dear Alexa.
And I I also the grade will be
interesting because uh,
the way and there uh.
Does the the evaluation follow a
different way of mind than me?
And I mean no one is necessary right or
wrong, but basically we're different,
so we will have to negotiate at some
point.
OK, tell Andrea,
we should tell Andrea we'll review this
so.
OK,
so today I decide that it is good if we
spend some time.
Talking about the runtime execution
environment.
The software is not just the PROGRAMMING
language, it's not judgment semantics,
but it's a complex artifact with a lot of
dependencies. I often tend to.
To say that software is like eggs,
there is a best before they eat because
you implement the software and you do
nothing and the software stops working.
At some point.
OK, so to some extent,
one may say that we did something wrong
because we started with the computer
science as a mathematical.
Apply discipline when everything was
basically.
Pure, correct. You do the verification.
So that is verification.
We do the requirements analysis and then
you write the software and this software
will run for it and it's.
And it's false there. Uh.
Sometimes, by accident,
I mean there are bugs.
Sometimes it's by the nature of the
problem we're addressing,
because most of the system we use today
are not doing mathematical computations
by itself. We're not anymore.
Mathematic computer science started in
the context of World War 2, I mean,
and so numerical computation in general,
cryptography and and then engineering.
So in the evolution, the prominent part.
In the 90s it was making computations and
that was the mathematical numerical part.
OK,
but then we introduced the UI and UI as
we commented,
there is event three reacts to an
external environment that can be.
Fully modelled into a formal model.
We're not, at least for now,
we're not able to provide a full model of
a human being,
which is the the one assessing the finger
thinking on the mouse.
And the same applies for Internet of
Things.
Where the dependency comes from the
outside automotive. In general,
all the controlling systems are governed
by the unpredictable states that may come
from outside.
Uh.
And then there is the fact that in the
beginning it seemed not so relevant,
but again,
because at the beginning we were
implementing the mathematics,
all three segments we were implementing.
It was, uh, so established discipline.
Then you can go and implement the lean
pack or some other library which
implement linear alt graph.
And you know that that library will be
used for very long time,
but this part of programming,
I won't say it's over,
but almost most of the.
Mathematical algorithms,
physical simulation,
etcetera has been mostly implemented and
so now we have to implement modern
systems and then you see.
The physicist.
Let's start using Python.
Biologists use Python.
It's a more interesting piece because in
physics division was C or C++.
The large has been programmed using C++
OK.
It was ******** fortune, OK,
and suddenly they started writing pipe.
Why?
Because they started modelling in their
system theories that are not yet
consolidated.
So an environment in which you can easily
change the code to update the model
becomes more appealing than it was before,
but suddenly you are exploring new ideas,
so.
Uh.
The whole point is software started as a
mathematical entity and now has become an
artifact.
They will be probably generated by AI.
Which capture a set of requirements and
elements that tend to evolve overtime.
Because the world evolves,
society evolves, service evolve,
and suddenly things that are very
important are not anymore,
and at the same time,
new things become important.
Including marketing because I mean I
didn't really feel the need for the new
UI in the iOS software.
So that's part of the life and this
process,
this is one of the first times that I'm
sharing this this opinion.
So I mean these are.
Real opinion, OK, take them.
It is the introduction to the set of
tools,
but I mean I'm trying to share with you
my views in terms of how in my lifespan
I've seen evolving software development.
And one of the consequences of this
evolution is that we spend less and less
time in software engine at the end of 90s
software development moving from
waterfall model.
It was a very rigid,
NASA oriented software development
methodology which was clearly devised to
implement a system that is meant to last
to a more agile form.
Our software development, uh,
acknowledging that software was uh.
I become a more.
Evolving, evolving, uh, structure.
So uh.
And now, now, because of AI,
many of the pillars.
Of software engineering are I mean
software reuse. Is that important?
When I open the cloud,
I found that I in the various demo of the
I I've asked it to implement the Mandel
broad fractile viewer at least 10 times.
And I never got the idea. Oh,
I already have the implementation.
Let's reuse that. I'm not doing the work.
Yeah. So in principle,
why should I write the software so that
it can be reused?
I can't get the sort of new every time.
At the same time you kind of come and are
raising like that.
So once we have a model and you just do
the specification of the.
Of software and it was from you.
So it's very software engineering as a
big different. No,
it's one part of software engineering.
So I'm not saying that software
engineering is that completely different.
Professor Di Vasi.
That we share with this recording will be
happy to hear me say that he was right
when he did his PhD in writing natural
language requirements for software
engineering.
OK,
so the requirement parts are clearly
there to stay because requirements
basically the attempt to tell in natural
language as specific as possible the
requirements from the system I need to be
developed but the other part.
Of software engineering that was
basically reusing human work.
Something libraries for cryptography,
etcetera, etcetera.
Some of them of course will remain. OK,
but some of them in principle you can
simply regenerate every time the code is
OK. OK,
so the part of software use I think it
will be.
Complicated to maintain and it is already
complicated.
Have you ever used pip in Python and sub?
OK, I'm sorry, sorry.
I'm really sorry for you. Uh,
so when you do PP install.
Have you asked yourself how many
libraries you're downloading on your
system?
And perhaps the most important question
is what happens if some implemented of
one of those packages will change the
semantics to software?
2.
And I mean you know what,
since every package depends on other
packages, you have all sorts of conflicts,
SQL dependencies,
one package may want one version of the
of of of a of a package and another a
different version and all these.
Should be taken care of,
which when you do PP install,
everything is fine.
Ask yourself in two years from now that
software that I did PP install people
will be still up and running.
If it breaks, how can I update?
After two years with packages that have
evolved on different routes and paths.
Thank you. I try on this.
I mean two years is the typical.
I don't want to see anymore that software
part.
So I'm I'm sure that the problem appears
after two months,
but realistic when you finish a software
survey.
So that was the two years,
but I agree that two months is probably
more up to date.
So uh.
I think in a advanced programming course,
it's becoming really important to.
Stop,
retouch things that goes beyond the
programming language,
which are runtime environments,
not in the sense of CLR or Java,
but in the sense of lifecycle management
or software and how it is evolving.
Mhm.
So uh.
The program originally was basically an
executable file with a well-defined
format which the loader,
the operated system is capable of loading
to the memory into the newly created
process memory.
And then jump to the first instruction,
go and have fun.
On Windows,
it's easy because it's dot EXE.
Extension that is a program.
Today the program is a more complicated
definition because when you have a web
server,
the program web server is up and running,
but I can still add a new dev folder into.
Some directory and yet a new web
application up and running it,
but I didn't compile anything and
moreover I basically compiled a dynamic
linking library, not an executable file.
Thanks to the mechanisms we discussed at
some point of the VLL.
So what's happening is that as the
software progress in its evolution,
it's too restricted to think that the
program is self-contained is an
executable.
Because we need as we move on,
we are creating frameworks.
So that we have to develop only the small
slots with the behavior we need without
having to rewrite anything. OK.
And so in this respect,
if I look at other software today,
the software today is a complicated
entity we trust.
Dependency in terms of packages of
libraries that your particular platform
provides to get some functionality that
has been already developed.
And there's one by.
The second part is it is very likely that
your program is not a fully executable
process.
It is more and more likely that it will
be loaded somewhere else,
one of the most popular.
Uh,
C stands uh is of course the web browser.
JavaScript, Reactor, AngularJS,
WebAssembly and so on are basically the
program is loaded by the browser,
which is a processor.
So basically your program is managed by
another program.
The same applies to, I mean,
plug these and everything.
Sometimes this happens in java.
net through the dynamic loader,
and this is one of the reasons,
to my opinion,
why CC and even Rust code is less popular,
I mean.
Is used and it absolves very important
tasks that are system level tasks.
I mean typically the building blocks of
our system are still C, Rust, C++,
etcetera.
But then the way you compose this huge
amount.
The amount of code we are collectively
developing and maintaining through
industry and open source contributors is
basically glued together through this
mechanism which range from.
Packages doing compilation and run times
which possibly alter the semantics of of
the code.
Remember when we studied the custom
attributes?
And I show you the web pages in C# that
have the annotations.
I use it as an example.
You say OK a low anonymous or HTTP get.
This this function,
this method should be exposed as a get on
the web server.
That meaning this basically in the
program I I said this is a method but I
also annotate it so that another program
can turn that method into a web endpoint.
So it is not anymore a problem,
it's just has been taken and attached to
to some external entity.
And 10 years ago I would have say that
these are components.
Honestly,
today components are too little to
explain this big thing.
Those are libraries, components,
web points, APIs, all these things, right?
And these things are growing so much that.
The Italian Public Administration.
Which is known to be very innovative,
digital and ahead of the rest of the
world.
At last produced an API based system
which is called PDMD in which all the
public administration offers service to
other public administration.
With authentication,
authorization and everything. OK,
so we are basically disaggregating our
software and create collections of
software and runtimes which together.
Uh, think by interoperability,
by martial running and machining,
and all the mechanics we introduced at
some point are able to use one each other
and provide some usable services.
OK, so when you're looking at like this.
And then you think of a program as a main
and then it is sort of really a main is
not a program, main is an exercise.
The program is tell me what is the
runtime,
not in terms of the programming language
support, but in.
Term of operating system and software and
how you use it.
And of course we also have to maintain
software, which is the other main part.
So for the first part we briefly and
shortly also because you're already using,
so it's OK, introduce Git.
It is basically what was standard for
repository and code evolution management.
And so that is the one part.
And the other part is uh um.
The set of programs that allows you to
manage all this complexity,
which of course have a root which is in
system administration, so Linux shares,
PowerShell on Windows,
Zshell on Mac and so on.
But clearly that is too few. I mean,
you can't write a system in bash.
It's too incomplete, but honestly,
it won't work.
You can pick up some other share,
but as we started trying to automate in a
systematically and managing very large
number of servers to serve very.
Large applications into one place led us
to develop a number of systems that try
to address the main problem of making
application run.
Provide in the application the
environment which provides to the
application all the required resources so
that it can perform its service.
So today if you give me a program,
it's not enough to some extent because I
basically don't have enough information
to to do.
So attempts originally were let's use
scripting engine.
Trev Puppet.
How many have heard about Chef,
Puppet or similar hands up?
OK, let's start with this.
What is back the?
What?
Our system to like Chef or Puppet or
Ansible, Ansible no one.
To.
Set up execution environment for
applications.
OK, so Chef, Pop,
Ansible are basically orchestration and
orchestrate speech so that if I need to
have the.
Bodi Bodi library installed on my 7500
systems. I say OK, this is the recipe.
This is the reason because the chef is
called like this. This is the recipe.
Please go on to all the notes and provide
the Bodi Bodi library onto.
All the noise. OK,
so that is basically the.
Infrastructure as a code is the the name.
Uh.
So they have become popular in our
paradine, which is the evolution of.
The uh.
Agile method so.
Have you heard about extreme programming?
OK.
OK, so people are good.
It's programming basically is you need to
you have to you need to coverage to break
your code so that you can improve it and
so on. It's very like major philosophy.
And and evolution has become something
that is called DevOps.
So a system where development and
operations.
So development is development operations,
especially in or data centers refers all
the to keep the systems.
OK. And so the in the DevOps world,
basically you meet the two and you have
very frequent cycles of upgrade.
You can shut down the system.
I'm pretty sure that if Facebook or or
TikTok or whatever shuts down the service
for two hours all the weeks it would be
upset.
For maintenance and so we had to devise
methodologies and software stack that
allows us to provision in a lightweight
form runtimes that allows us.
First, to quickly deploy a new system,
which means to provide the right
execution environment to the program we
we brought second.
Uh.
That is able to manage for scalability.
Because the the the guy which writes the
Google index code or the search code
writes for processing a query,
but then you need the system that scales
up to server millions of query per second.
Third,
the ability to have a different version
of the same software, who is it here?
So yeah, and typically the goal is OK,
I made this upgrade to the software.
We don't know if it works,
so there is alpha and beta.
OK, it works. Will the users be happy?
Of this and so the solution is you know
what? I start both services,
old and new version.
Then I use a software which is called
load balancer which hides the service
itself.
And simply say OK, you pick this request,
you pick the request and so on.
And so it's OK 5% of the people new
service, rest the whole service.
And if you're happy, OK,
let's finish and install everything. OK,
so in this super complicated world.
The only thing that we found.
I think mostly because of people.
Andrew not just is you know what at the
end of the day if I can save all the
directory with all the packages that two
years ago I downloaded and I can keep.
The operating system stable around that
software can run for it.
I mean.
But now I need a way to freeze the
software stack starting from the system.
Whenever I upgrade the system,
some libraries will change,
some libraries the changes library will
influence packages that are used in those
libraries.
And so on and support and your
application will crash.
So every update on any components
potentially can break the system.
That's that's the thing. So.
There are, of course, methods.
To try to avoid obvious breaking,
one of these is unit testing.
How many of you have heard about unit
testing?
Good.
So unit testing is a natural way to face
this.
Let's take.
Let's be more concrete.
And take some example.
Uh.
I will take.
This, but this is not the project.
Which I was looking for.
I mean, I'm looking also for that,
but it's.
Oh.
Uh.
Uh uh.
Let me take Oraculum,
which is in this in this respect. I mean,
it's not because Oraculum is beautiful,
it's just because I wrote the code base
so I know that there is something I'm
looking for it.
So just the as a a quick example again
runtime management.
Someone had really an idea on Java to say
hey you know what since we have this
ability to load the things I can write
the program which basically.
Execute methods that are labeled to some
somehow so that I can run multiple tests.
You need tests,
so you're familiar with the with the
concept, so I won't spend much on this.
The only thing which is worth saying that
is a good example of existing environment.
Basically I'm writing all these.
Uh.
Oh,
it is complaining because I don't have I
have to upgrade the.net version.
It's OK and so test method.
This is like a small main which is the
unit test,
but I want to run these many programs one
after the other end.
Checks some properties.
So basically the test method annotation
informs the runtime which is not the
executable.
So this is not a program as a whole,
but it's a bunch of function you want to
test and some runtime.
In this case,
the end unit runtime will load these
things and run all the tests and give me
a beautiful UI. OK.
OK. And and and so on. OK, so this is the.
You need test.
Now also the unit test is.
Complicated because you're checking only
some features of your software.
In fact the software also other tests are
run such as the regression test.
Because not all the corruption may be
caught by unit testing.
So it's unit testing is.
A good thing to do,
but not that important.
I mean not not exhausted. OK, so.
How can we ensure,
given the status of the art,
the friend and unit testing requires
development skills if you if the software
is not open source then?
You know that the solution is getting
back, so who cares about the testing?
Let's find a way to freeze the full
computing stack.
First answer, virtual machines.
Something that I use it to free this that
you can see around Windows 2000 or even
Windows NT4 on top of the visualization
system and and so the system of the
virtual machine gives me a stable
environment that I can.
Even think of not upgrade.
I don't care because it's sandbox and of
course then I have to protect from the
outside from for cyber security attacks.
But apart from that can freeze this
software and let this software to last
for very long time.
Until nobody understands anymore nothing
of that thing and then you will pay for
implement an equivalent version with new
technology.
So basically that now the problem is.
So how many of you have installed a big
machine?
That's good.
So what is now that you all install the
what is the drawback of the machine?
Me.
Yeah, everybody.
Uh, it it's the must be, you say? Yeah.
So yeah, the hypervisor we had.
Basically we need a program, uh,
which is called hypervisor.
Technically it also slows down.
I'd like to explain to you how does it
work. The Egg Advisor. This is beautiful,
but I don't have time,
but basically just to give you the
problem is that there are interrupts.
They have to be called by against the
reducing sensor or other that should
percolate down to the cost of the
reducing system. OK,
and so it is very sophisticated.
There is a slowdown of the machine,
but thanks to VMware.
Where this slow down gradually went down
to.
The amount which is acceptable 10% would
say OK advantage I can have Windows,
Linux,
Mac running on the same system and
disadvantage overhead.
Hello.
Forced to start any with the machine you
have to move.
And more resources because if I have
three Linux boxes,
I'm paying 3 file systems, 3 kernels,
3 whatever. OK,
this is so the solution which is
basically.
Thing I want to cover the most day and I
want to show you with practical example
interesting stuff are basically bound to
a technology that has been mostly
developed in Google.
How many of you have developed the
container?
That's a lesson. That's good. That's good.
What is a container since you're all
familiar with the container?
OK.
Oh, yes, this, this. I mean,
actually in that source that that,
but technically what it is, a container.
It's not ADM. It's not, no.
As the meeting.
Is that it's about the container shipper
that the as a container in the and the
and the that the smaller.
Small small container are the single
application that don't have I mean inside
of the and the just the dependency the
application the and the not.
All they'll get the system inside.
This probably can be a good requirement
for a container system,
but actually the definition depends on
the container itself.
What it is a container?
Have you always installed the container?
You should know.
From a an operating systems standpoint,
what is a container with the help?
A container is a set of rocesses.
Of the current operating system.
Which are confined in the structures of
the current.
Through a mechanism which in Linux is
called C groups container groups.
So that when you execute system APIs,
the operating system will give you back a
subset of the information.
If I look at the process,
a list of the processes even though.
A container is a process like any other
process in the operating system.
This container will see only process
related information, so main works,
networks, etcetera,
limited to each container group.
So I in score.
The containers are a way to partition the
tables of the operating system so that
you can hide from the operating and from
a process information about other process.
Why?
Because in programming and before also in
your privacy system, names are everything.
So if you hide a name,
the resource will be accessible.
Right.
So now you know what it is that what you
installed or run.
So a container is a process or a set of
process. When you do, when you do fork,
you create a new process.
That process will belong to the same C
root.
And so it will see the resources of the
neighbors.
This is one of the two parts of the
containers.
It's our processes in AC group of the
current on Windows.
There are containers and they use.
With the subsystems,
but I mean if someone speeds us through
the eye,
but they are available on by the way.
We will talk later.
What is the second major ingredients of
containers?
What do you mean by?
I mean one is the process,
but we know that application require data.
So yeah,
like ingredient of a container is the
data.
What is the interesting about the
container data?
Did you guys hear me?
Few goals. I mean then.
The.
Give me one second, Stefano.
Oh, oh.
So.
Uh, the basically.
The problem uh uh,
so one of the possibilities on machine uh
is the disk.
I have two Ubuntu, some very certain.
I pay twice the cost to disk with the
same data.
Then of course the storage can do the
duplication or some other techniques,
but I mean some of you that will attend
the ICT infrastructure course.
This one, uh, next semester.
We'll learn more about that.
But in any case,
there is a problem with the file system
occupy a lot of space.
So the other ingredient is a differential
file system.
So a format that has been standardised
that allows you to express basically like
the git. It's like the git,
but apply to a file system.
So you have the the git expressing other.
Segments.
These segments have versions and so you
can inherit from the Ubuntu image and
then change the file system and you get a
differential file system.
So on the system there will be a copy of
the.
Parent container and and and every
container then has the differences so you
don't have to pay much in terms of pays.
Of course this also makes very very
fragile.
In and and slow the differential file
system. In fact they say OK,
but please the real data don't put on on
the differential file system. OK.
So.
Help.
We can introduce the last two and most
important things so that you have a
reasonable perspective of what's going on
in the software distribution space.
This that I'm showing you is not the only
option, of course.
But it's becoming this de facto standard
of most software development.
So I decided to focus on this.
Of course there are still application
that are installed with the good old
install shield or some variant of Windows.
There are the packages of Mac, etcetera.
But these are basically the traditional.
They are the package manager that
typically allows you to download the
packages, etc. And so all these.
But containers in this respect are
becoming a key element that you have to
understand,
especially if you wanna be able to.
Debug your application and so I decided
that to explore the runtime.
It was good to spend time on this, OK.
So.
Question.
You have to pay attention. No,
I'm I'm joking to raise the hand. Oh, yes.
Oh, don't you. We have drives. OK,
so this is a double file.
What is the purpose of this?
Find.
OK.
The reality is that things are much
simpler than this in the sense that
basically there are operation which say
that that that basically say OK.
Those are.
Um.
One second,
step back and we'll restart 'cause I.
OK,
can I run Windows and Linux container on
the same Linux machine?
Oh.
You will use it on things so.
You're saying no. Why?
That's why we're using it. Oh, it's not.
It is. It's not why we use containers.
It would be nice to be able to run both
operating system.
Technically there is a configuration that
allows you,
but basically the reason is what I.
Just talking.
It's a data structure in the curve,
which means one curve.
So it is true that they can run on a
container on Ubuntu and the other with
red out. This is true, but the kernel,
it will be the only one and it's the
kernel of the operating system that is
run on the container.
But the kernel has become reasonably
stable in terms of API,
so the kernel changes,
but in terms of implementation.
But the system calls are basically stable
since a very long time.
And so if you look at operating system,
the operating system is made by the
kernel,
plus a lot of dynamic linking libraries.
The evolving part of the system is mostly
on the DLLS that are stored.
Into the this that are loaded by the
processor.
So whenever you're using the C runtime,
the C runtime gives you F open to open a
file. Internally it uses the open 3D, OK.
The open is all is stays the same,
but if you upgrade and improve the
standards in that time,
you can change the F open implementation
without touching the kernel.
Do you agree with this?
So basically.
Since this the kernel is stable and the
the the run the the runtime of the
application is loaded and depends upon
DLL that are loaded into the process and
are stored in the file system,
then I can create.
A good illusion that I'm running
different distribution on the same.
Beware,
with container it's almost impossible to
run a five version ago Linux,
some version five version ago and and
Linux today. OK,
it typically don't work because also the
current.
But different distribution just differ
from the file system and DLLS,
so you can do it.
So every process will load a different
set of DLLS and we're using a different
way the system calls and you get the
flavor of redactor versus.
And then you want to over there. OK,
set up price in Windows, but no,
I can't mix and match because the kernel
loaded is one you're saving because you
have only one kernel loaded.
And all these, all these are processes.
Which I think in the operating system.
So one operating system, many processes.
Processes have the impression to run on
different operating system,
less overhead than running virtual
machine pay price to pay.
Less isolation,
no network identity because in the
virtual machine you can have a little
leak talking to and you'll see them
answer like a network feature in the
container slope you are connected to a
bridge.
Networking off it. OK, having said that.
I can go where I was.
This file simply execute the commands
that you can even run at the common line
one after each other.
So I mean it's a model interaction and
basically this thing says OK.
The cooperation I have are I can create a
new container which means in the essence
of my system from an existing one,
so from a a set of existing.
Fires.
And uh,
execute the commands in the current
kernel using that file system.
It's nice when you when you see the
containers this way,
everything becomes much clearer unless we
simply.
So this one is beautiful and I encourage
you to.
Uh.
You can download the community version of
Visual Studio.
I don't know if Visual Studio.
Uh.
If Visual Studio code supports the same
scaffolding,
but basically this is the template that
Microsoft generates when you want to add
Docker to your project.
OK, and I'm using it to teach.
I learned a lot from. I mean,
I probably I really learned about Docker
by studying this code because most of the
Docker file are pretty obvious and so you
end up looking and say OK, that's.
Easy.
This one is more tricky and it's
therefore it's interesting and there is
this.
URL that I'm gonna share on the on our
team.
Uh.
I share it in the.
Docker template.
This is a good a good read.
So I suggest you to have a look if you
want to understand because basically they.
Want to introduce in a development
environment support for the office so
that you can processes running.
OK, why?
Because when you start the process in a
container, how do you debug this thing?
How can you attach this thing that is?
There is still Docker exact,
there are ways,
but I mean there is no easy way to debug.
OK, so Microsoft said, OK,
let's support the debug inside a
container.
And so I think that this is interesting.
Of course I I I'm pretty sure that
similar things are available also on
other platforms.
I use this, so I let's start with this.
OK,
let's try to read now what's happening.
From somewhere.
So there is a standard public repository.
Take an image that is called ASP dot ASP
net version 8.
Let's call it base.
So this way of working is called a model.
I mean there is a mode,
so the subsequent commands after from
will be executed assuming that this
container is loaded.
So basically a new differential file
system is created starting from this the
runtime of Docker.
Will fetch the image and install it.
So even if it's an old image,
it's still there stability.
Then you say OK,
there is a user that is called app.
This is executed as a user app.
The working directory is root app.
So it is like I did the I entered in this
new environment I say CD slash cap.
And then you say expose port 8080. OK,
now this is interesting about containers,
but it also relates to the software.
I mean sockets are fit and finite you
have.
How many orts?
65K Yes, more or less. Yes, 16 bits, yeah.
And every port is now bound to a service.
Port 8 is HTTP,
443 is HTTPS and so on and so forth,
25 SMTP and so on. OK,
so I say OK this container outside.
Can expose port 8080.
But because the computer so.
An operating system can start multiple
instances of the same container.
If I run twice this thing I will have
that the first starts and take hold of
port 8080.
The second one will crashes because 8080
is already taken.
But when I program,
I need to know the port.
So the solution has been you know what?
There are two ports,
TCP ports in containers.
One is the internal one.
And so this means that these containers
expose only one port to the outside,
which is 8080.
But then when the container will be
started,
you will say OK port 8080 of this
container corresponds to port 80 of the
machine you map.
It is like a net at home when you do the
network address translation OK and so in
this way.
Uh, you fix that, OK?
This is the definition.
Now we change image.
So this this building process is
interesting because as you can see we are
creating multiple containers and a
sophisticated build. So this one.
Starts from a different container,
which is the.net SDK version 8.
We call it builder.
We pass an argument.
In the environment,
you remember environment variables.
What are environment variables?
Environment variables are a set a pair,
a set of pairs name value that are
defined and attached to the process and
in Linux when in Unix when you when you
fork.
The new process will receive the
environment variable,
so you can write your software and in
fact.
There are APIs to read the environment
variables and then your software can be
can change its behaviour using the
environment variables.
Now environment variables are rather.
Annoying and in fact they are little used
in model system for configuration because
it's difficult to pass structured values.
They are flat list,
so if all the application use environment
variables it will become a mess.
So in principle you can use for
configuration,
but for decades we changed the
configuration into files, ETC on Linux,
the register on Windows. OK,
so basically we said OK,
let's store the configuration of our
application somewhere else because
environment variables are too complicated
to use.
Then containers brought them back.
Now environment variables are beautiful
and more and more programs have learned
have learned how to use to be configured
using environment variables because they
are a handy way.
To configure software from containers. OK,
Spotlight, let's move on. OK, work deer.
You go into the source directory,
then you say I want to copy.
By definition,
by default the copy is from the host to
the container. So copy from the local,
from my shell, from the current directory.
Into the science directory in the
container.
So this changes the the differential file
system. It adds a new file under science.
Then you run.
A process in that container, so this.
net restore will be run inside the the
container where the SDK includes also the.
net command, so it's already there.
And you you execute the restore which is
basically like pip install.
It downloads all the dependencies that
are stored in the C# project.
Then you say OK copy from local.
There is the current directory where the
source code is to the.
Current directory inside the container
SFC source.
Now we enter into the directory signs.
And we run the build command.
So now I'm building the the application
inside the container.
You may say, why are you doing this thing?
I mean,
why don't you compile on the local system?
Because the container is more similar to
the target environment,
so the dependencies.
Of your software are closer to the
runtime environment,
less likely to find bugs due to the
software stack.
Much better.
And in fact this thing on Windows works
because Microsoft implemented the Windows
Linux subsystem.
So you have Linux running inside Windows,
otherwise it won't work.
Then you say OK finish.
So build is basically containing the the
the source and the binary version of the
program. OK.
Now oh, this is a rename for clarity.
The build image I call it also publish,
but this is really for clarity.
Otherwise it's it's an alias.
You said again the environment variable
and then you say OK.
net publish which is a common of the
runtime.
This project we the build the
configuration.
Environment variable in the directory of
publisher.
Uh.
And don't use a post. OK,
so this is a command that I run into the
target container.
Right now, last,
do you remember the base container?
Before,
which is what so far is only this
container.
This container basically contains only
the binary, the runtime, not the SDK,
the compilers.
Needed to run the application.
And then you say, OK,
let's call the runtime image as final.
Just remember that this is the final step.
Let's go into the slash app directory and
then you say copy.
This time we say the source explicitly
from publish, but publish is this,
which is basically that and so from the
container publish.
Take the directory slash app slash public
publish and copy it in the directory
slash app of this container.
Finally, the entry point of this is.
net with the DLL as an argument.
Hmm.
Is it?
No, they're not.
Technically you're cloning the container.
So when you say from base,
you say OK base, leave it base.
I create a new container based on base.
Can you read?
Oh, no, no, these are.
So here we have basis from container.
Build this another container.
Uh.
Publishes another container.
Final is another container.
So you create 4 containers,
but basically these are volatile
containers.
It will be discarded at the end of the
process.
Yes, but during the during the the, the,
the, the builder,
those are different containers.
I think that the and then start building
or they keep alive until the. No, no,
I mean thank you for the question.
I mean, thank you for the question.
Containers are not something that is that
are running. Containers are.
We said that containers are made of two
things,
a differential file system plus a number
of processes in the same container.
So I can insist that even though there
are not processing because you still have
the.
The device is differential. OK,
so the container exists simply it has no
running activities.
But there is no container value.
Container running is just a container
that has at least one process running
that is a running container.
I hope now we have a a better
understanding of the container technology.
So.
In this way we are able to create a
container that can be published on a on a
directory so that other people can
download it as a version.
So every change can be compiled to a
different version of the container.
Right and and it is self-contained.
It is contained.
So all the PP installed files, all the.
net dependencies,
all the libraries needed in that
particular pressure are basically frozen
in this differential.
File system and as long as we don't
change too much the Linux kernel API and
we preserve the semantics of the existing
calls,
this container will be able to run and we
can continue to upgrade the the kernel of
the system to make it boost,
more flexible, more efficient, whatever.
OK,
so that's the core and it's crucial in in
software development because and in fact
Google originally,
you know for which Google,
for what Google implemented this
technology.
Search because it was impractical to run
as the problem they had. They don't want.
They didn't want user to be able to
access data from other searches.
They may contain sensitive data.
OK,
so they needed some isolation so that if
some search process crashes,
you don't have the full search engine
crashes or in this case. So they said OK,
yes,
but the virtual machine is not a good
idea.
It's too expensive because we receive.
Billions queries per day.
And so they they worked on this
technology so that basically every search
that you perform on Google is run on a
different container,
which is just like starting a process.
Work destroy the process so everything is
always cleaned up,
but the container gives to the code a
consistent environment and so they can
make the search engine evolve over time
thanks to this.
OK, now if you have a uh.
The containers.
It is fairly natural to describe your
software as a set of different services
because apart from the desktop
application and even there you can
discuss server side services are
typically created by using multiple.
People application because we specialized
every layer in the application stack to
perform well some function.
So for instance you may have you may have
the.
This is a web application. OK,
So what you may have the the web server
that can be ng Apache OK.
And this is the front end and this
software is specialised to implement all
the HTTP protocol,
update the HTTP protocols,
implement all the restriction,
all the configuration policies, rewrite,
reverse proxy, DLS certificates, etcetera.
OK, all the huge complexity.
And that's the first layer.
Then I may have a single layer which is
your application server, your program.
And now was a break down the HTTP server
without having to worry about security
standards etcetera,
because there is the front web server
which they care and just reverse the
request.
To be to to your application.
OK and and and in this way you can use
Tomcat for Java, Castle or.net, Python,
whatever for Python and so on. OK.
And that's happened because that is a
simpler web server just to serve the
requests and transform them into code
execution.
Then unfortunately a lot of application
requires databases.
So I may need another ITS running.
How do I debug this thing?
How can I develop something so
complicated and be sure that this can?
Can be thrown into the execution.
The answer is that you have the ability
to compose containers.
Docker composer is the easiest form and
this is the example of a Docker compose
file and it is also.
An example of the YAML file.
Remember Mark Kaplan at some point I
mentioned. This is exactly a YAML file.
Again, save effort in parsing so.
Let's look at the.
Uh, so there are these.
There is a closed services and we have.
Three services in to run this application.
The first Service is the front end.
The front end uses as image engines,
so the front end is running using the
engines.
Restart in case of failure always.
You map.
So you say, OK,
if the container tries to open this file
inside his file system,
ETC nginx confdefault.conf,
which is the default place of the nginx
configuration.
Map it onto the local file system in this
file and Jinx.
Uh.com OK.
So as you can see,
containers are nice because can be easily
hooked.
This means that if someone can have
access to your machine,
all the containers are broken,
of course as a root, but.
Then you say, OK,
ports port 80 of the container maps to
the system port 80.
Port 443 maps on to port 443. OK, easy.
So this is the first year.
Then you have.
No, sorry, the application tier signs.
So this is the software.
Environment.
You see why environment has become is now
popular again because you can specify all
the variables to configure in this file
and so without having to read files,
mapping files, etcetera,
everything is easy.
So here I say OK port 8080,
port 8080 on port 8080.
So this means that with this I'm saying
port 8080 of the container is mapped on
port 8080 of this system.
Depends on.
Of course when you start composing you
say OK, yes I can run,
but I need the DP please and I'm sharing
the network.
This is not a CS admin courses,
so if you're interested you come to the
other course.
Otherwise you ask the AI how the networks
in Docker works.
It's out of the scope of today and now I
say OK,
I want to run SQL Server 2022 as a
container and.
The administration password is this and
I'm recording and projecting this because
it's a debug password.
Of course this is not the password of the
of the real database,
but it allows me to quickly.
Manage and and debug things.
I accept the end user license agreement
because otherwise it won't start. So yes,
I agree and and the port is this and you
know what?
The slash up data directory of the
database maps onto my system science data.
OK,
so with this that you've got an idea of
what's going on with all data.
So the first part was OK, this is how we.
Which is becoming a natural way to
package software,
and this is how you can combine the
software you package it into complex
systems.
Now if you have all this this machinery,
it's fairly easy, not trivial,
but fairly easy to create a cluster that
is capable of running contents.
The most popular implementation of in
source is called Kubernetes.
So Kubernetes is basically a scheduler of
container and it is likely a place where
your software will land into.
So the reason because I decided that at
least one class should be devoted to this
is that the first question that you may
get is how do I?
I debug this thing.
How can I check something?
Because I can show you a running system.
Oh.
OK.
Right.
Oh, let me zoom in. There we are.
So this is the way we are deploying.
Part of our application as a university,
we have a registry,
a Docker registry where we push images
and we download the images.
So whenever we release a new version,
we publish on the registry the new
version and we update and we pull on.
The systems using that image,
the new version.
OK, so if I ask if I say PS dot A-A,
as you can see there are no processes on
the machine.
If I look the the there is no software if
I try to run.net here.
Note net.
OK,
even though the container of in this case
is based on.net. OK,
this is because if I do Docker,
Docker PS now I'm asking let me show the
containers running.
And we have engines and we have version
07.3 of Sibilla.
OK, now I can say Docker exact C.
Bash.
This is how.
Hmm, sorry, dash TI.
Otherwise, OK, it's not interactive.
So I just started with this command a
process bash inside the container group
of the container. So now if I say PS oops.
Oh, yes.
Kil is still there. Grab is still there.
I can list and if I look at user beam you
will find that there are very few
comments of the standard comments because
with containers I can restrict the number
of comments that are deployed.
To only those commands that are required
to run the environment so that if some
attacker breaks in,
not only is it confined,
but it's also asked to struggle to
install the commands because they are not
available.
OK.
And so this is how and now since also
this has been generated in the same way
as you we just there is the app and in
the app.
There actually there is the output of
compilation using the Docker file that we
just commented and as you can see all the
versions needed to run this thing are
here frozen forever.
In my directory.
If I wanted to move the service,
I am only to restore the Docker,
pull the image,
run the image and that I want to make it
parallel. I run 2 instances,
I put a load balancer on top and so on.
So this is the good thing.
With Kubernetes you scale out to multiple
servers. You can say OK,
move all the containers from that machine
to that machine so that I can service the
server and so on.
And so you can do all the operations,
but this is also the contract between and
it is becoming the dominant contract
between the software,
so the developers and the operations,
which is the IT admins that have to run
in a secure way these things.
For the curious of you,
this is a script that I found online
which basically transform the common
Docker compose into a Linux service.
So I simply say uh.
Uh.
Restart the system control, CB restart,
restart all the commands and so when the
system starts it was use Docker Composer
and if you look at the Docker Composer.
There is.
And the image is on our registry.
There are some volumes,
there are some ports mapped,
some environment and then there is the
front end with the certificates.
Running and jinx.
But if I go here and I say N Jinx,
there is no N Jinx, right?
So I hope with these two have guided you
first into the problem of where the
software is.
Is executed.
Second,
how can we preserve all the dependencies
that we're creating that are more and
more difficult to track?
And the answer can be different.
I mean you can always have a scripts that
format a machine,
install all the software and then copy
the files.
But the most common option as of today.
Is you create containers and then the IT
administration provides an environment
where you can run containers.
Container has become the contract between
you.
The developer and the people in charge of
running the system container may be
popular by people install and this is not
a joke because it was becoming so
complicated.
That I mean they existed before,
but the Docker has become so popular
because it was so difficult to preserve
all the dependencies that are in this way
and that's it.
And so this is a good thing.
But also another example is the NVIDIA
software stack on Linux if you have.
And afford and then and then the the the
software is distributed as container
because at some point it was so
complicated to recompile things, do this,
do that, et cetera,
that eventually we just said, OK,
you know what?
This is the core thing. That's it.
Everything you need.
You don't have to spend enough day
struggling to make my software work.
And now it's become not standard. Yeah,
the spectrum of software environments and
really made their own down lecture.
Where something like I remember to repeat
also where something like in the
environment.
Oh, so why don't we the?
It's complicated because in in the in
this world of, you know,
open source and you unfortunately don't
have to you need any driving license to
write software.
Anyone can go out there and write a
software that becomes popular and no one
really plans that.
The need for it.
So the Python environment developed in a
in a moment in which Docker were not so
available and it's a Python only solution
with each other similar features,
but it's more likely to be broken.
Because it depends on the LS of the
system.
So when you go and upgrade the system,
there is some light events that then will
break.
Whereas if you restore the container pipe
and maybe inside use the Python hand.
Sense it in some case,
then you can get the best of the both
world,
but there is really some of the lab in
this.
Right.
Other questions?
OK. Thank you. Have a nice week, Canada.
Next week we exercise ourselves.